前情提要
Previously on Foundation…
帝国将灭亡 我们做的一切都无法避免它的到来
The Empire will fall. Nothing we do can prevent this.
威胁和平 就要付出沉重代价
Threaten the peace and pay a dear price.
告诉在世和亡故的人 你们未能拯救他们
Tell the living and the dead you failed to save them.
人们称之为“穹窿”
They called it "the Vault."
-波利 -波利 回来
-Poly! -Poly, come back!
我想见幽灵
I wanna see the ghost.
它在周围投射了一个阻止人们靠近的力场
It projected a field designed to keep people away.
从来没有人突破空域
Nothing has ever gotten through the null field,
以后也不会有
and nothing ever will.
（改编自艾萨克阿西莫夫的小说）
每个世界都有幽灵
Every world has ghosts.
每所房子都有幽灵出没
And every house is haunted by them.
即使是帝国宫殿
Even the palace of the Empire.
尤其是帝国宫殿
Especially the palace of the Empire.
（400年前）
你去哪了
Where have you been?
和系统程序员在一起
With the systems programmers.
你最近和他们在一起的时间 多于和我在一起
Lately you've been with them more than with me.
（克里昂一世）
你给他们安排了一项艰巨的任务
You've set them a large task.
有必要找人替换他们吗
Should we look to replace them?
他们能完成任务的
They'll see it through.
德默泽尔 我能信赖你吗
I can count on you, Demerzel?
确保任务完成
To see it through?
当然 克里昂
Of course, Cleon.
不仅是完成任务
And not just that.
还有其他一切
Everything.
我总是认为在我走后你会留下
I always assumed you'd stay on after I was gone.
但接近人生的尾声 我才意识到
But it occurred to me, in the near-darkness of my life…
任何事情都不是理所应当的
I shouldn't take anything for granted.
我对帝国忠心不二
I'm loyal to the Empire.
是的 但帝国会对你忠心不二吗
Yes, but will the Empire be loyal to you?
它对你的同类从未仁慈过
It hasn't always shown benevolence to your kind.
你变得多愁善感了 几乎接近伤感
You're becoming sentimental, verging on maudlin.
我即将死去
Well, I'm dying.
而我留下的是一个支离破碎的世界
And I'm leaving everything in pieces.
你对继任者不满意吗
Are you unhappy with your successor?
我们仍可以考虑婚姻和子嗣这一方案
We can still revisit the idea of marriage and an heir.
德默泽尔 毕竟你不是人类 也可能正因如此
Demerzel, for all you are, and maybe because of it…
有些事情 你永远不会理解
there are things you will never know.
也许有一天我会理解死亡
I may someday know death.
是的
Yes.
但我认为你不会觉得死亡来得太快
But I doubt you will feel it arrived too soon.
我应该目睹星桥的建成
I should have seen the completion of the Star Bridge.
我 我的头脑 我的眼睛
Me. My mind. My eyes.
我们应该一起乘车上轨道平台
We should have ridden up to the orbital platform together
俯瞰我们所创造的一切
and looked down on all that we had made.
会有那一天的
And one day we will.
你的王朝将永远延续
Your continuity is assured.
（400年后）
-你常常想他吗  -你知道我是怎么样的
-Do you think of him often? -You know the way I am.
我从不忘记任何事或任何人
I don't forget anything or anyone.
（星桥爆炸事件19年后）
大帝永远在我心上
Empire is always on my mind.
平台的轨道运行正加速失效
The platform's orbit is dying at an accelerated rate.
至少物理学家是这么说的 他们担心它会掉下来砸到自己头上
Or so say the physicists, who worry it'll just fall on their heads.
担心这种事是他们的职责
Their job is to worry over those things.
这不是我们的职责吗
Is it not ours?
也许仍是你的 但这已经不归我管了
Perhaps it is still yours, but no longer mine,
也不归他管了
as it is no longer his.
如何度过最后一天由你决定
How you spend this last day is up to you.
每一个你都不一样
Every one of you is different.
对于这点 我很怀疑
Somehow I doubt that.
但多谢你尝试 让我在临死之时感到自己是独一无二的
But thank you for trying to make me feel unique as I shuffle off the stage.
对他来说 这个过程最困难
It was hardest on him.
当时能即位的只有婴儿黎明
He only had the infant Dawn to place on the throne.
一个有着他双眼的婴儿
A baby with his eyes.
在任何方面都与他一模一样 但仍只是个婴儿
Identical in every respect, but a baby nonetheless.
当我想到他时 那是我所想到的画面
When I think of him, that's what I think.
他也有你
He also had you.
大帝 请去见伊兰师傅 他在等待你的最后试衣
Please see Master Ilan, Empire. He's waiting for your final fitting.
开始吧
Shall we?
细节是完美的
The details, they're perfect.
用什么缝边
For the pick stitching?
翡翠吧
The jade, I think.
让开…
Shoo, shoo.
对不起 大帝
I am sorry, Empire.
我瘦了
I have lost weight.
-您的身型一定… -我在萎缩
-I am sure your frame is-- -I am shrinking.
我与世界的距离变得遥远
The world is beginning to see me from a distance.
这套衣服令人惊叹 伊兰
The garment is singular, Ilan.
身穿这套衣服升天是我的荣幸
It will be a privilege to wear it at my ascension.
谢谢 大帝
Thank you, Empire.
我们继续吧
-Shall we finish the job? -Oh.
伊兰 给这姑娘一个机会
Ilan, let's let the girl have the stage.
黄昏兄弟 我不知道你在这里
Brother Dusk? I didn't know you'd be here.
安纳克里昂 狄斯比斯
Anacreon. Thespis.
不知道在我走后 你是否还会说起他们
I wonder if you will speak of them after I'm gone.
我们打败了蛮族 将他们驱逐出帝国
We have broken the barbarians. Cast them adrift.
你希望我们说出什么你还没说过的话吗
What would you have us say that you haven't said?
不知道 我还在决定 有哪些话是我还没说但该说的
I don't know. I'm still trying to decide what to say that I haven't said.
关于外围星域吗
About the Outer Reach?
关于任何事 关于我们是否 真的有权控制这一切
About anything. About whether any of this is truly within our power to control.
我说话的机会已不多 我不想浪费它们
However many words I have left, I would hate to waste them.
你说起外围星域的时候已经是在浪费了
You waste them when you speak of the Outer Reach.
我说到谢顿
I speak of Seldon.
一个已死去多时的人
A man long dead.
且很快就被遗忘的人
And soon forgotten.
那意味着他的言语 对这个帝国已经毫无价值了吗
Does that mean his words have no more worth in this Empire?
兄弟 帝国很强大…
Brother, the Empire is strong--
克里昂一世的功业
Cleon I's legacy.
不知道有没有办法拯救它
I wonder if there's a way to save it.
用推进器稳定它 将它送到星系更深处
Stabilize it with propulsive lifts? Push it out into the heavens?
为了什么
To what end?
为了不摧毁克里昂一世梦想中仅存的部分
To the end that we not destroy the last remnants of Cleon I's dream
因为我们并没有梦想
for lack of our own.
黄昏兄弟
Brother Dusk.
克里昂一世的伟大梦想是我们 不是星桥
We are the great dream of Cleon I, not the Star Bridge.
梦想者
The dreamer.
学者
The scholar.
炼金术师
The alchemist.
（克里昂11世 画家）
和我
And me.
（克里昂一世 梦想者）
我一辈子都尝试模仿
I've tried my whole life,
但我从没成功做出这个表情
but I don't think I've ever been able to make that face.
走吧 你的兄弟们为你准备了最后的礼物
Come. Your brothers have your last gift.
我想感谢你们 我的兄弟 为我准备了这顿丰盛的美餐
I would like to thank you, Brothers, for this beautiful meal.
每一口都能尝出你们的用心
I can taste the care you put into each bite.
我很感激你们抽时间费心这么做
Your time and your attention is deeply appreciated.
不用客气 兄弟
You're very welcome, Brother.
但这不是礼物
But this is not the gift.
欢迎来到川陀 帝国中心
Welcome to Trantor, the eye of the Empire.
已经太久了
It's been so long.
他真伟岸 对吗
He was glorious, wasn't he?
心怀尊敬 享受和平
Please respect and enjoy the peace.
是的
Indeed.
我们将建造更伟大的事物 以纪念他 也是为了你
And we will build something greater in his honor. For you.
心怀尊敬 享受和平
Please respect and enjoy the peace.
你不能来这里 你是知道的
You can't be here. You know that.
我不可能是第一个 想看自己最年幼时样貌的人
I can't be the first one who wanted to see my youngest self.
这正是我们立下这条规则的原因
Which is why we made the rule.
我从没听过这首歌 还是说听过
I've never heard that song before. Or have I?
怪不得大帝如此爱你
No wonder the Empire loves you so.
我发现自己无法将那孩子视作无辜者
I find I cannot quite look on that child as an innocent.
就算谢顿是错的
Even if Seldon wasn't right…
这样也是不合乎自然规律的
there is something unnatural in that.
你得走了
You must go.
你应该休息
You should rest.
看着自己出生 感觉真奇怪
Strange, watching yourself being born.
睡吧 明天见
Sleep. I'll see you tomorrow.
我今晚看到你了
I saw you tonight…
你在看我们的第一位兄弟出现在星桥遗址
watching our first brother in the old Star Bridge.
我们还不够吗
Are we not enough?
这是你想念他的原因吗
Is that why you miss him?
不是的 亲爱的兄弟
Oh, no, sweet brother.
有你就足够了
You are enough.
只是你们总会离我而去
It's just that you always leave me.
你已成长为伟大的人
You have grown into our greatness,
黎明兄弟现在已是白昼
Brother Dawn, now Day.
谢谢你 黄昏兄弟
Thank you, Brother Dusk.
新的黎明刚醒来
And the new Dawn, just awoken.
你将有漫长而美丽的未来
You have a long, beautiful day ahead.
黑暗兄弟 是时候了
Brother Darkness, it's time.
由你继续完成梦想
The dream lives on in you.
因为你让它生机勃勃
Because you kept it alive in you.
没关系的
Shh. It's okay.
你不会有事的
You're all right.
一切都安好
Everything is all right.
不
No.
有什么不对劲
Something's wrong.
德默泽尔
Demerzel.
我从不忘记任何事或任何人
I don't forget anything or anyone.
大帝永远都在我心上
Empire is always on my mind.
活着即意味着与幽灵相伴
To be alive is to know ghosts.
如果用心听 我们能听见幽灵的低语
We hear their whispers if we listen.
（17年后）
我们都笼罩在预言的阴影下
We are haunted by prophets, all.
（克里昂14世）
黎明兄弟 你确定要抹去壁画吗
Are you certain you want it erased, Brother Dawn?
是
Yes.
它对我来说已过时了
I've outgrown it.
我们忽视亡者 让自己陷于险境
We ignore the dead at our peril.
随着帝国历经了另一代克里昂的统治后
And as Empire cycled through a generation of Cleons,
基地开始对端点星进行殖民
the Foundation began colonizing Terminus.
帝国低估了哈里 我们都低估他了
The Empire underestimated Hari. We all did.
哈里成功预测 克里昂将流放他 而不是处决
Hari had predicted the Cleons would opt for exile over execution…
他门下信徒的终点将是端点星
that his followers' end point would be Terminus.
他们到达后的每个方面 都已经预测好了
Every aspect of their arrival was predetermined…
殖民者何时着陆
when the colonists would land…
他们在何处建造哨站
where they would build their outpost.
所以可以想象他们有多惊讶
So imagine their surprise
当他们发现那里已经有一个建筑了
when they discovered that something else was already there.
以谢顿之名啊 那是什么
What in Seldon's name is that?
勘测结果里没有这个
It wasn't in the surveys.
我们应该回去吗
Should we go back?
回哪里 马莉  从一开始这就是一趟单程的旅程
Go back where, Mari? This was always a one-way journey.
-我去看看 -不行 我们一起去
-I'll check it out. -No. We go together.
劳莉 你还好吗
Lowre, are you all right?
-没事… -走吧
-Yeah. Yeah. -Come on.
-我只是有点头晕 -走吧
-I'm just a little light-headed. -Come on.
回去
Get back.
阿巴斯 往回走
Abbas! Get back.
人们称它为穹窿
It became known as the Vault.
数十年来流传着无数关于穹窿的传说
And over the decades, countless myths grew up around it.
有人说它是外星人留下的古老文物
It was an ancient artifact left by aliens…
还有人说它是克里昂们建造的监控站
a surveillance outpost sent ahead by the Cleons.
所有殖民者都很清楚
All the settlers knew for certain
穹窿不让任何人靠近
was that the Vault wouldn't allow anyone to approach it.
所以他们远离那里
And so they kept away.
人们将慢速舰拆除
The slow ship was scuttled…
用它的框架和零件建造庇护所
a refuge built from its bones.
曾经神秘的地方成为日常的场所
And what was once mysterious became mundane.
她的老师们说她很难教导
Her teachers say she's difficult.
她是边缘人
She's an outsider.
很好
Good.
你没用心听我的话 阿巴斯
You're not listening to me, Abbas.
她是一个梦想者
She's a dreamer.
她分心了
She's distracted.
她是一个思考者 和你一样
She's a thinker, like you.
她并没有分心
She's not distracted.
她是心无旁骛
She's aware.
看看她 她对它着迷
Just look at her. She's fascinated by it.
它很美
It's pretty.
它很危险
It's dangerous.
你认为里面有什么
What do you think's inside it?
我们不知道
We don't know.
那你怎么知道它很危险
Then how do you know it's dangerous?
走吧
Come on.
（现在）
飞吧
There you go.
飞得远远的
Get away.
有一天你会吓到我 到时你就惨了
One of these days you'll get me, and you'll be so sorry.
你看起来很精神嘛
You're looking good.
是啊 穿着很搭
Yeah, coordinated.
-哪些地方搭了  -右靴和左靴
-Which parts? -Right boot with left boot.
我居然没发现
How did I miss that?
野外工作的进展如何
How goes the wild work?
刚刚在高地那边巡逻回来
Just got back from patrolling the highlands.
苔藓床的面积在缩小 冰鹭已经南飞了
Lichen beds are shrinking. Ice lunes are already heading south.
意味着我们将迎来暖春
Means we're gonna have a nice warm spring.
你不会想念这一切吗
Tell me you don't miss it.
想念什么 硫磺的臭味
What, the stench of sulfur?
冻疮
And the frostbite?
不 你比我更适合当守卫者
Nah, being a warden suits you a lot better than it ever did me.
哇 这只很大啊
Wow. That's a big one, hey?
是的 母主教爪 可能有600公斤
Yeah. Bishop's claw, female. Maybe 600 kilos.
过去几周的深夜 它一直试图突破围栏
She's been testing the fence late at night the last few weeks.
我给它命名为梅宝 它总是单独行动
I'm gonna call her Maybel. She's a loner.
塞佛 你为什么一大清早叫我来这里
Salvor, why have you got me out here at this time in the morning, huh?
我知道自己的女儿是在拖延时间 说吧
I know when my daughter's procrastinating. Come on.
我做了一个小测试
I did a little test.
空域有些不对劲
Something's wrong with the null field.
你为什么选择在此时测试
And what made you check it now?
不知道 一种感觉
I don't know. A feeling?
我测试了 我获得证据了
I checked it out. I got evidence.
当然 你告诉她了吗
Of course. And have you told her yet?
我想先让你知道
Wanted you to know first.
谢谢 但这事应该告诉她
I appreciate that. But it is for her to know.
并强调你有证据
And stress the evidence part.
多亏了谢顿博士的工作
Thanks to the efforts of Dr. Seldon,
克里昂12世建造了我们的庇护所
Cleon XII established our refuge…
在计时方面
In terms of timekeeping,
水钟更加准确
the water clock is the more precise instrument.
是 但那需要水才能运行吧
Right. But it also requires water to work, doesn't it?
显然如此
Well, obviously.
乔德修士 水用光了怎么办
What happens when the water runs out, Novice Jord?
如果用日晷 我们只需要晷针 也就是突出来的叶片
For a sundial, all you need is the gnomon. That's the blade sticking out of it.
当然还需要…太阳
And, of course… the sun.
哈里谢顿将灭亡后重建文明的任务 托付于我们
Hari Seldon entrusted us with rebuilding civilization after the collapse.
我们不能假设任何事
We can't assume anything.
我们不能假定未来的幸存者必能识字
Whether or not our future survivors will be able to read,
或他们将说什么语言
or what language they'll speak.
我们甚至不知道他们将分布在哪些星球
We don't even know what worlds they'll be scattered upon.
如果他们身处天鹅座元星
What if they find themselves on Cygnus Prime,
而唯一的水源来自泣藤呢
where the only moisture to be gained is from weeping vines?
所以 这座水钟确实更准确
So, yes, this water clock is more precise,
但日晷更实用
but the sundial is more practical.
我们无法为后代将面临的每一个环境 或特殊状况做准备
We can't provide for every condition or contingency our descendants will face.
同理 我们不能保存每一项发明
By the same token, we can't preserve every innovation,
所以我们必须选择 并一直做出各种选择
so we have to choose and keep choosing.
直到灭亡的那天
Until the fall comes.
我会选水钟
I'd have picked the water clock.
如果你还在这里受训 那你确实有权选择
And you could have, if you were still training here.
抱歉 这么说…
Sorry, that was--
我知道你现在的职务很适合你
I know you're suited to where you are,
保卫大家的平安 确保基地存活
keeping us safe, making sure the Foundation survives--
是确保你能存活 基地…
I'm making sure you survive. The Foundation--
是同一件事 我们就是基地
It's the same thing. We are the Foundation.
我不是 但你有信念 那很好
I am not. But you believe. And that is fine.
不 别把基地说得像邪教一样
No. Do not make this sound like a cult.
我们这一代人知道 真正的狂热教徒是怎样的
Some of us in our generation know what real religious fervor looks like.
你到底想不想知道 我来是想告诉你什么
Do you even wanna know what I came to tell you?
你知道我不喜欢靠近它
You know I don't like being near it.
爸爸说你会想要证据 所以你必须亲自来看
Dad said you'd want evidence, and this you gotta experience for yourself.
空域正在扩大
The null field is expanding.
空域原本从那里开始 现在延伸到这里了
The field used to start there. Now it starts here.
如果它继续扩大 我们也许需要让镇上的人撤离
If it keeps expanding, we might need to clear out the town.
我记得第一次在这里发现你时的场景
I remember the first time I found you out here.
那时你四岁 半夜里
Four years old, middle of the night,
站在它的下方 仿佛…不受任何影响
standing right under it like it was… nothing.
我叫你的名字 你不转身
And you wouldn't turn when I called your name.
对 我以为它在呼唤我
Yeah, I thought it was calling to me.
幽灵
The ghost.
像一位想象中的朋友
Like an imaginary friend.
我伏在地上 试图爬到你身边 但是痛感太强烈了
I lay on the ground and tried to crawl to you, but the pain was too great.
你只是…
You just…
看着我
looked at me.
我不懂为什么穹窿能伤到你 却伤不到我
I couldn't understand why the Vault was hurting you but not me.
你是特别的 塞佛
You're special, Salvor.
你一直都是
You always have been.
那为什么要保密
Then why keep it a secret?
你的父亲和我不想让别人对你差别对待
Your father and I didn't want people treating you differently.
是 但是他们确实这么做了 妈妈 一直都是
Yeah, but they do, Mom. They always have.
我让他们感到不舒服
I make them uncomfortable.
就像穹窿一样
Just like the Vault.
它此刻在呼唤你吗
Is it calling to you now?
没有用言语
Not in words.
给我看证据吧
Make your case.
我觉得它正在苏醒
I think it's waking up.
你和其他的百科全书撰写者
You and the other encyclopedists,
你们在为遥远的危机未雨绸缪
you've been preparing for some distant crisis.
但我认为危机已经到了
But I think it's here.
就在此时
Now.
吉雅 凯尔 雨果来了
Gia! Keir! Guys, Hugo's here!
-雨果来了 -雨果来了…快去呀
-Hugo's here! -Hugo's here! Hugo's here, come on.
-雨果来了 -来呀 雨果
-Hugo's here! -Come on, Hugo!
-雨果 -雨果
-Hugo! -Hugo!
雨果
Hugo!
快瞧 走吧
Whoa. Look at that! Come on.
-从这边走更快 -嘿 小心 嘿
-Cut through this way! -Whoa. Hey, now. Hey!
-你捉不住我 -从这边走
-Oh, you can't get me. -Through here.
快点 大家 快去 走吧
Come on, guys. Come on. Hurry up! Let's go!
波利 快跑 快点
Poly, come on! Hurry up!
雨果…
Hugo! Hugo!
-雨果 -雨果
-Hugo! -Hugo!
庄严发誓 雨果
Four-sworn, Hugo!
女士们 先生们 你们几位大人需要我帮些什么忙
Gentlemen, ladies. What can I do for you grown adults?
给我们带东西了吗
Got anything for us?
克雷尔巧克力 慢用
Korellian chocolate. Knock yourselves out.
我们不想要巧克力 有啤酒吗
We don't want chocolate. How about some beer?
等你的胸口长毛了再问我要酒喝吧
How about you come back and see me when you got hair on your chest?
别像无助的小宝宝一样乞求我
And don't come begging for it like wayward puppies.
我们才不是乞求 我们是交易
We're not begging. We're… trading.
这样啊 拿什么交易
Is that so? What for what?
我们幽默的话语和有趣的陪伴
How about our sparkling wit and company?
没兴趣
Hard pass.
这样吧
Tell you what.
如果你们几个小崽子帮我卸行李
If you clowns could help me load out,
也许我能给你们找一些 与你们的年龄相符的玩意儿
I might be able to scrounge up something a little more age-appropriate for you.
成交 我愿意
Deal. I'll do it.
我们都愿意
We all will.
那去吧
Go on then.
-走吧 -走吧
-Come on, guys. -Come on.
-凯尔 接住 波利 -我在这边
-Keir, catch. Poly. -I'm here.
好臭
That smells terrible.
当然 这是用在橡胶靴上的密封剂
It should. It's sealant for my gum boots.
洋葱比我想的更多
More onions than I expected.
我可能拿错食谱了
I may have used the wrong recipe.
那就太不幸了
That would be a tragic mishap.
没事
It'll keep.
有什么问题吗
What's wrong?
我的厨房里有个男人
There's a man in my kitchen.
你这次待多久
How long are you here?
29个漫长的小时
Twenty-nine long hours.
星系其他地方怎么样
And how's the rest of the galaxy?
很大
Oh, it's big.
你有空应该去看看
You should see it sometime.
是吗
Should I?
艾琳娜四号星
Irina Four.
只有一片大陆 但全都是热带
Only one continent, but it's tropical all over.
那里的昆虫和狗一样大 也同样黏人
It's got bugs the size of dogs and just as cuddly.
我把药品留下了 带走了水果
Dropped off medicine, I picked up fruit.
这就是任性供应商的流浪生活
Such is the itinerant life of the wayward purveyor.
-你把水果送去哪里了  -长庚星
-Where'd you take the fruit? -To Hesperus.
你对它的了解已经和我差不多了
Which you could describe as well as me by now.
但我偶然去到一个星团
But I was off on a whirlwind tour of this little cluster.
他们开始交易之后就停不下来了
Once they started trading, they couldn't stop.
工人 糖 朗姆酒和现金的四边交易
Little rectangular situation of workers and sugar, rum, cash.
如果你觉得自己的星球有很多卫星 你应该见识一下他们的
You think you've got a handful of moons, you should see what they got.
天空像是洒满了硬币
The sky looks like spilled coins.
洒满了硬币
-Spilled coins? -Mm-hmm.
我还真想看看
I'd love to see that.
你应该去看看 离开这个冰球
Well, you need to go. Get off this ball of ice.
-我在这里有责任 -但这不是你的选择
-I've got responsibilities here. -Oh, but you didn't pick them.
对 但那仍是我的责任 而且…
Nah, they're still mine. And…
有可能知道存在原因 但却不知道原因是什么吗
Is it possible to know you've got reasons and not know what they are?
你对这个星球而言很重要的原因
Reasons you're important to this place?
有可能 这么想有点自大 但有可能
It's possible. A little egotistical, but possible.
我的意思不是我很重要 我是说我不能离开
I didn't say I was important. I said I can't leave.
说到离开 你想现在吃晚餐还是之后再吃
Speaking of leaving, would you like dinner now or after?
之后吧
After sounds good.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
出了什么问题吗
Is something wrong?
只是有种奇怪的感觉 我去边界附近走走
Just a weird feeling. I'm gonna walk the perimeter.
因为奇怪的感觉来自那里
What, because that's where the weird feeling is coming from?
不 那感觉来自这里
No, that is in here.
我只是散散步
This is just a walk.
所以如果我说 “等我穿好裤子” 你会说什么
So if I said, "Let me get my pants," you'd say?
接下来的25个小时不准穿裤子
No pants for the next 25 hours.
-你等下会生气吗  -不会
-Will you be mad later? -Never.
你在那里做什么
What are you doing out there?
停下
Stop!
停下 现在是宵禁时间
Stop. It's after curfew.
有人吗 有人在吗
Hello? Hello?
你是谁
Who are you?
怎么回事
What the hell?
我听到枪声 怎么了
I heard a shot. What's up?
我是疯了吗 那艘船像是安纳克里昂的
Am I crazy, or is that ship Anacreon?
你的确是疯子
Oh, you're crazy.
但你说得没错
But not about that.
现在有三艘了
And then there are three.
-呼叫他们 -我们已经这么做了 没有回应
-Hail them. -We already have. No answer.
他们也不理会我们的进近矢量
And they're ignoring our approach vectors.
我们应该派一辆穿梭机去见他们吗
Should we send one of our shuttles to meet them?
未装配武器的穿梭机
Your unarmed shuttles?
这些可是护卫舰 武装飞船
Those are corvettes. Gunships.
他怎么在这
Why is he here?
因为他知道武装飞船长什么样
Because he knows what gunships look like.
而且他是狄斯比斯人
Also, he's Thespin.
从爆炸事件后就离开了
Been off-world since the bombings.
不可能 那样的话 你…
Impossible. That would make you--
快70岁了 但我有一半的时间 都是在传送点间冷冻睡眠中度过
Pushing 70. But I spent half that cryosleeping between ports.
去安纳克里昂送货的时候 外星的身份比较有利
When you tow freight to Anacreon, it pays to be blood-neutral.
-安纳克里昂受帝国制裁 -成熟点吧 路易斯
-Anacreon is under imperial sanction. -Grow up, Lewis.
也许只是个意外 也许他们偏离航道了
Maybe it's a mistake. Maybe they wandered off course.
他们根本就是想趁我们不注意偷偷着陆
They're literally trying to sneak in under our radar.
我们这是一个科学哨站 没有任何有价值的东西
We are a scientific outpost. We have nothing of value here.
市长 安纳克里昂人 曾在本星球着陆过吗
Mayor, have the Anacreons ever made landfall here before?
没有安纳克里昂人 也没有狄斯比斯人 30年来没有任何人着陆
No Anacreons, no Thespins. No one in 30 years.
根据帝国法令 他们一概不得踏足端点星
Under imperial edict, Terminus is off-limit to all of them.
这一定与穹窿有关
It's gotta be connected to the Vault.
什么
What?
空域正在扩大
The null field's expanding.
-我昨天发现了 -速度多快
-I noticed it yesterday. -How fast?
第二天 安纳克里昂人就出现了
The next day, the Anacreons showed up.
严格来说 我们是帝国哨站
Technically, we are an imperial outpost.
大家都知道安纳克里昂跟帝国有过节
And Lord knows the Anacreons have a bone to pick with the Empire.
你的意思是穹窿也许是安纳克里昂…
Are you suggesting the Vault might be an Anacreon--
我的意思是穹窿知道些什么并作出了反应
I'm suggesting the Vault knew something and reacted.
也许它甚至曾提醒我们
Maybe it even warned us.
你是说穹窿向你发信号了 因为你与众不同
Are you saying the Vault was signaling you because you're somehow, what, special?
塞佛是一个异类
Salvor is an outlier.
我们必须想一想计划是否预测到…
We need to think whether the Plan could have possibly predicted--
忘了计划吧
Forget the Plan.
谢顿已经不在了
Seldon's gone.
你们什么时候才会开始独立思考
When are any of you gonna start thinking for yourselves?
好了 够了 我们不需要把情况弄得复杂
All right, that's enough. We don't need to make this complicated.
安纳克里昂不理会我们的呼叫 他们侵犯了帝国领空
The Anacreons have ignored our hails, and they are violating imperial aerospace.
我们很清楚该采取什么行动
Our course of action is obvious.
我们将上连通讯浮标
We'll uplink to the communications buoy
到达下一个自转通讯空窗期时就这么做
as soon as we hit the next rotational window.
我们呼叫帝国 他们将派人来这里
We'll call the Empire, and they will come.
你要去哪
Where are you going?
去查看军械库
To check out the armory.
如果安纳克里昂人先于帝国援兵到达
If the Anacreons come knocking before the Empire,
我想知道我们能集合多少武力
I'd like to know what kind of violence we can muster.
有多久没有检查这些了
When was the last time these were broken down?
-我们只是有点懈怠 -如果需要 我有一把离子手枪
-So we're a little complacent. -I've got an ion pistol, if that helps.
妈妈 策展店里有什么用得上的东西
Mom, anything we could use in the curation stores?
几把手斧 一条纺织者星的牧羊人投石带
A few hand axes, a shepherd's sling from Weaver's World.
-我不应松懈的 -这不是你的职责所在
-I should've been on top of this. -Not your job.
-不是吗 我该确保你们的安全 记得吗  -来…
-No? I keep you safe, remember? -Come on. Come on.
在这种时刻 我一般建议喝点酒
Generally I propose alcohol at a juncture like this.
（通讯连接 帝国编解码器启动）
通讯空窗期到了
Rotational window's open.
握手协议 只需几秒钟
Handshake protocol. It just takes a few seconds.
（通讯连接失败）
怎么回事
What's wrong?
通讯浮标没有回应我们的任何呼叫 失去信号了
Comms buoy's not responding to any of our pings. It's gone dark.
换一个试试
Use another one then.
没有其他的了
There isn't another one.
所以说这意味着什么
So, what does that mean?
我们无法联络上帝国
We can't contact the Empire.
继续尝试联络 别慌
Well, keep trying. Don't panic.
也许只是因为流星雨 会过去的
Could be something as simple as a meteor shower. It'll clear.
恰好在安纳克里昂飞越之后
On the heels of an Anacreon flyby?
假设安纳克里昂人计划在这里着陆
Assuming the Anacreons intend landfall here,
他们还有多久会到达
how long before they arrive?
根据他们现在的进近状态 我认为还要40个小时
Based on their current approach, I'd say another 40 hours.
妈妈
Mom.
那是什么
What is that?
心理历史学
Psychohistory.
哈里的所有研究 以数学等式的形式表现
All of Hari's work expressed as a mathematical equation.
是我在他葬礼后的那晚从他办公室拿走的
I took it from his office the night after his funeral.
他的计算结果为我们 进行这一切工作的原因提供了理据
His numbers are the basis for why we do what we do.
飞船上原本有两个人能够真正理解它
On the ship, there were two people who could actually understand it.
哈里谢顿和盖尔多尼克
Hari Seldon and Gaal Dornick.
你能理解它吗
Can you make anything of it?
我 不太可能
Me? No, not likely.
塞佛 如果你是计划的一部分
Salvor, if you were part of the Plan,
那我会更容易相信这一切
it would make it a lot easier for me to believe in all this.
不奇怪
Yeah, well, big surprise.
值得一试
It was worth a shot.
值得吗
Was it?
我和你说过 不同不意味着特别
I told you, different's not the same as special.
通讯浮标出故障了
Comms buoy is down.
这是不祥的预兆
That is an ominous happenstance.
你最好还是离开
You should probably hightail it.
是吗
Oh, yeah?
安纳克里昂人两天后就会到达 也许更快
The Anacreons will be here in two days. Maybe less.
你去任何地方都比这里安全
You would be safer anywhere but here.
每年此时的风景都很美
The scenery is so beautiful this time of year.
一望无际的废墟 满是冰冻的鹭粪
Vast wastelands of frozen lune shit.
我是认真的 雨果
I'm serious, Hugo.
你一向都是
You tend to be.
我哪都不去
I'm not going anywhere.
这不是属于你的战役
This isn't your fight.
是吗 那是谁的
Oh, yeah? Whose fight is it then?
谢顿的
Seldon's?
那么也不是你的战役
Then it's not your fight either.
和我一起离开吧
Come away with me.
我不能这么做
I can't.
为什么
Why not?
因为我必须保护他们
Because I have to protect them.
活着即意味着与幽灵相伴
To be alive is to know ghosts.
帝国忌惮哈里 因为他能够预知未来
The Empire feared Hari because he could forecast the future.
但事实上他做的不过是重新检视过去
But, in reality, all he was doing was reexamining the past.
你想要什么
What do you want?
注意观察规律 我们就能预测接下来将发生的事
Pay attention to the patterns and we can presage what comes next.
活着即意味着与幽灵相伴
To be alive is to know ghosts.
如果用心听 我们能听见幽灵的低语
We hear their whispers if we listen.
又是你
You again.
嗨
Hey there.
是什么伤到你了 梅宝
What got you, Maybel?
会有点疼
This is gonna hurt.
别紧张
Easy.
放下武器
Drop your weapon.
你是谁
Who are you?
塞佛哈定 端点星的守卫者
Salvor Hardin, warden of Terminus.
安纳克里昂人不得进入帝国的领土
Anacreons aren't allowed on imperial soil.
你来这里做什么
What are you doing here?
亡者的幽灵出没于 我们旧日家园的废墟中
The ghosts of the dead haunt the skeletons that were once our homes.
他们环绕着我们
They surround us.
他们对我们所拥有的一切虎视眈眈
And they're hungry for what's ours.
字幕翻译：易晗